<resources>

    <string name="second_floor_text">second floor</string>
    <string name="first_floor_text">first floor</string>
    <string name="choose_language">Choose language</string>
    <string name="backBtnText">HALLWAY</string>
    <string name="audioBtnText">AUDIO</string>

    //Dogadjaji kod nas i u svetu
    <!--<editor-fold desc="Room1">-->
    <string name="room1Title">Events in Serbia and Europe</string>

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page1">-->
    <string name="room1Page1Title">Historical circumstances</string>

    <string name="room1Page1Text">
        The history of Europe in the 18th century was marked by the Revolutions and upheavals.
        Those changes did not occur only in a political sphere, but were preceded by the ideas
        initiated by the French Enlightenment philosophers Charles Montesquieu, Denis Diderot,
        François Voltaire, and Jean-Jacques Rousseau. By criticizing the political establishment
        and the church, they inspired and brought about many changes in those times.
        The French Revolution, the Fall of the Bastille on July 14, 1789 marked the ending of
        absolute monarchy. The National Assembly published The Declaration of the Rights of Man
        and of the Citizen which proclaimed that all men are free and equal in terms of their rights,
        that laws are the same for all citizens, and that sovereignty is grounded in the idea of a nation.
        The abolition of feudalism in France marked the outset of a new era.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="sarl_monteskje">Charles-Louis de Secondat</string>
    <string name="sarl_monteskje_detail">Charles-Louis de Secondat</string>
    <string name="deni_didro">Denis Diderot</string>
    <string name="deni_didro_detail">Denis Diderot</string>
    <string name="fransoa_volter">Франсоа Волтер</string>
    <string name="fransoa_volter_detail">Франсоа Волтер</string>
    <string name="zan_zak_ruso">Jean-Jacques Rousseau</string>
    <string name="zan_zak_ruso_detail">Jean-Jacques Rousseau</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page2">-->

    <string name="room1Page2Text">
        Serbia was not excluded from new historical currents. The Pashalik of Belgrade, an
        administrative unit of the Ottoman Empire was shaken by numerous crises pervading the Empire.
        Interminable conflicts escalated in the form of insurrection on February 14, 1804 in Orašac,
        a place in Western Serbia. Đorđe Petrović Karađorđe was chosen to be the leader of
        The First Serbian Uprising. That was the beginning of the Serbian revolution which ended
        in 1835 with liberation and abolition of feudalism in Serbia. The First Serbian Uprising
        (1804-1813), The Second Serbian Uprising (1815-1817), the autonomy gained through
        hati-sheriffs, the sultan’s handwritten decrees with immediate effect (1830 and 1833),
        and the abolition of feudalism enabled political and economic liberties as well as social
        equality to the Serbs in Dukedom of Serbia. The social climate in the liberated Serbia
        necessitated the formation of national identity whose foundations were the newly erected
        National Theatre and the newly established National Museum.
    </string>

    <string name="narodno_pozoriste">National Theatre</string>
    <string name="narodno_pozoriste_detail">National Theatre</string>
    <string name="narodni_muzej">National Museum</string>
    <string name="narodni_muzej_detail">National Museum</string>
    <string name="karadjordje">Đorđe Petrović Karađorđe</string>
    <string name="karadjordje_detail">Đorđe Petrović Karađorđe</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    //Beogradska velika skola
    <!--<editor-fold desc="Room2">-->
    <string name="room2Title">Museum and Grand School</string>

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page1">-->
    <string name="room2page1Title">The Story of the Building</string>

    <string name="room2Page1Text">
        The house in which the Museum of Vuk and Dositej can be found today is one of the oldest
        residential buildings in Belgrade. It was probably built during the first half of the 18th
        century for a member of the Turkish elite, and maybe even for the governor of the city.
        The exact year of the construction and the names of the first residents remain unknown to us.
        Being a prime example of the Ottoman-Balkan architecture, this house is luxurious and
        represents one of the rare two-storey houses in Belgrade. The house\'s garden was once
        surrounded by a high wall, but the wall is preserved only around the entrance gate.
        Several economy buildings stood around the house as well.
        The house is vertically divided into two sections: harem and selamluk. Selamluk was strictly men\'s
        part of the house. The rooms of selamluk are today used as offices for the Museum\'s administration.
        Harem was home to the family (women and children). Both parts of the building have divanhana,
        places that were used as living rooms.
        Going through the centuries, the house was used for different purposes. At the end of the
        18th century, it served as the French Consulate, the only diplomatic office in Belgrade under
        the Ottoman rule. During the First Serbian Uprising the house was home to the Grand School.
        After the end of the Uprising, the building welcomed Turkish families again. Since the
        liberation of Belgrade in the middle of the 19th century, until the Second World War,
        several Serbian merchant families lived in this house.
        The building was reconstructed in 1948, and in the next year it was presented to the newly
        established Museum of Vuk and Dositej. Since 1979 it has been a part of the National Museum in Belgrade.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="maketa_zgrade">Model of the museum building</string>
    <string name="maketa_zgrade_detail">Model of the museum building</string>
    <string name="franta_mali_tusem">Dositej’s lyceum</string>
    <string name="franta_mali_tusem_detail">Franta Mali,  Dositej’s lyceum, 1935.</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page2">-->
    <string name="room2Page2Title">The Story of the Grand School</string>

    <string name="room2Page2Text">
        Monasteries, churches and priests were concerned with education in Serbia until the
        beginning of the 19th century. The First Serbian Uprising against the Ottoman Empire
        started in 1804 and it led to the liberation of Belgrade in 1806. Serbian revolutionaries
        wanted to make a good use of this temporary peace and they started to build a new country.
        After the proclamation of the Constitution, the organisation of schools was a very important subject.
        Church lost the leading role in education in Serbia, and the new Serbian government started
        to control the development of schools. Ivan Jugović, a teacher from Sombor, persuaded
        Karađorđe that foundation of a higher education school in Serbia is of great importance.
        Karađorđe was the leader of the First Serbian Uprising and the founder of Serbian royal
        dinasty Karađorđević. Thanks to Ivan Jugović and Karađorđe, the Grand School was founded on
        September 12th, 1808. It was a predecessor of today\'s high education schools in Serbia.
        The Grand School was opened to all Serbian boys, and it wasn\'t concerned with the status
        of the students\' parents. In order to start attending the Grand School, boys needed to know
        how to read, write and calculate. The number of students was rapidly growing and it\'s building
        started to be too small. The Grand School was then moved to a building across the street,
        where we can today find the Museum of Vuk and Dositej. The School was active until 1813
        when the First Serbian Uprising was terminated. Students at the Grand School were
        Vuk Stefanović Karadžić, Karađorđe\'s son, sons of Serbian leaders and other boys.
        All the subjects in one class were held by one teacher. There were no textbooks,
        so the teachers mainly used foreign materials.
    </string>
    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    //Dositej Obradovic
    <!--<editor-fold desc="Room3">-->
    <string name="room3Title">Dositej Obradović</string>

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page1">-->
    <string name="room3page1Text">
       In the ground level of the Museum there is a small sculpture – sketch for a monument of
        Dositej Obradović which is located in Student’s park, close to the edifice of museum.
        The sculpture is a sculptural work of Rudolf Valdec. In that sketch, as on the sculpture too,
        it is noticeable that Dositej is distinctive by his dressing at the time which was in European style.
        He is represented in move holding a hat and some books in left hand, and a stick in his right hand.
        Over the stick gently passes a part of a topcoat which sways as if some light wind followed its motions.
        On the sculpture’s foundation, that decorates Student’s park, on its frontal side is written
        “To Dositej Obradović, grateful Serb people”, and on the lower part of the foundation are
        engraved the words: “Learns travelling, looks through centuries”, famous Dositej’s quote.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="rudolf_valec">Dositej Obradović</string>
    <string name="rudolf_valec_detail">Rudolf Valdec, Dositej Obradović, bronze 1911.</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page2">-->
    <string name="room3page2Text">
        Dimitrije Obradović is born likely around year 1739 in Čakovo, in Banat, on the territory
        of today’s Romania. He lost his parents in his youth, and his uncle, who took care of him,
        sends Dositej to do craftwork. When he was fourteen, he run away to monastery Hopovo in
        Vojvodina, where he became a monk and got a new name - Dositej. In monastery he began to
        reflect about ascetic life, but soon he was disappointed with life in monastery where he
        did not found those magical stories about saints that he was reading for years. Besides
        that, he met the profane literature and embarked on one new world which represented
        different moral and life principles. Three years after that he leaves monastery life behind
        and begins constant journeys for his studies and academic improvement.
        He lived and did his studies from Small Asia, through Balkans to Russia and England.
        While on journey, he studied languages and literature of different nations, absorbing
        current cultural educational and social reforms that were occurring in Europe.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="manastir_hopovo">Monaster Hopovo</string>
    <string name="manastir_hopovo_detail">Unknown author, Monaster Hopovo</string>
    <string name="mapa_dositejevih_putovanja">The map of Dositej’s travels</string>
    <string name="mapa_dositejevih_putovanja_detail">The map of Dositej’s travels</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page3">-->
    <string name="room3page3Text">
        The author arranged this work as an invitation for subscription to a book Sovjeti zdravog
        razuma which he planned to print.  In the letter, where he speaks to his friend Haralampije,
        a priest from Trieste, Dositej explains his reasons to publish the book written in Serbian,
        the national language.  He considered that the book where are collected the thoughts of
        world’s greatest minds shall be of grand use to people. The cause to publish the book
        written in national language was in coherence with current world reforms in that time,
        where, likewise the Dositej’s, the idea was that books arrive also to people living in
        distant and inaccessible regions, who, if know how to read, will be able to understand the
        written words. Further, Dositej stood up for religious equality which helped him to rise up
        above antique comprehension of religious nationalism. He points out that for world hatred
        and evil are culpable irrationality, self-love and vanity, and not the difference in laws
        and religious affiliation, and therefore, he will write for mind, heart and the nature of a
        person. Precisely because of that, this letter is Dositej’s manifest of the ideas of
        enlightment, and therefore it occupies a special place in the history of literature.
        The same year it is printed his first autobiographical book with the name
        Život i priključenija which is the beginning of Serbian modern literature in national language.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="pismo_haralampiju">Letter to Haralampije</string>
    <string name="pismo_haralampiju_detail">Letter to Haralampije, 1783.</string>
    <string name="dositej_obradovic">Dimitrije Tirol, Dositej Obradović</string>
    <string name="dositej_obradovic_detail">Dimitrije Tirol, Dositej Obradović</string>
    <string name="zivot_prikljucenija">Life and Adventures</string>
    <string name="zivot_prikljucenija_detail">Life and Adventures, Leipzig 1783.</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    //Vuk Stefanovic Karadzic
    <!--<editor-fold desc="Room4">-->
    <string name="room4Title">Vuk Stefanović Karadžić</string>

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page1">-->
    <string name="room4Page1Text">
        Made in bronze by sculptor Surov – Vezilić Vuk is presented as a mature man dressed in
        European suite with characteristic details: fes on his head and long, curled, moustache.
        This sculpture is positioned in front of Vuk`s room. Vuk Stefanović Karadžić was born on
        November 6th 1787. in village Tršić, near Loznica, in west Serbia. In Karadžić’s family all
        children born before Vuk died very early, so he got name Vuk, which means wolf, so he can
        be protected from witches and ghosts – as people believed.
        ,,When woman can’t gave a birth to a child, she gave to her son name Vuk (wolf) because
        she thinks that whitches are eating children, and people can’t kill or hurt a wolf.
        That’s why they gave me that name”. – this is Vuk’s explanation about his name.
        As young man Vuk got sick from terrible rheumatic disease, so his left leg (knee) stayed
        cluttered until the rest of his life. Despite of that, Vuk’s life was long and rife.
        He used stool, staple and stick while he was walking.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="vuk_karadzic_bronza">Vuk Karadžić</string>
    <string name="vuk_karadzic_bronza_detail">Surov - Vezilić, Vuk Karadžić, bust, bronze, 1886</string>
    <string name="stap_stula">Vuk’s crutch, peg leg and cane</string>
    <string name="stap_stula_detail">Vuk’s crutch, peg leg and cane, leather and wood, Vienna, 19th Century</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page2">-->
    <string name="room4Page2Text">
        Vuk learned writting and reading from his nephew Jevto Savić – Čortić which was the only
        literate man in  that area of Serbia. He continued his education in school in Loznica, but
        he didn’t finished it because of his illness. Later, he continued his education in monastery
        Tronoša. In monastery they forced Vuk to look after animlas, and not to learn – that’s why
        his father got him back home. In one short period of his life he was studying on Great school
        in Belgrade. Vuk learn most of those things by himself because he was hardworking, curious and vigorously persistent.
        Later, he figured out some irregularities in Serbian language and ortography, so he decided
        to reform and bring close to ordinary people. Main idea of his work was that language is
        the main medium in communication between people, so the books on that language have to be
        understandable to every human. After First Serbian Uprising (1804 – 1813), as the majority
        of young, educated, people, Vuk left Serbia and go to Vienna where he is going to stay until
        the end of his life. He got back in Belgrade only twice, and during the second visitation
        he was situated as member of Nahi’s Court and borough of Belgrade.
    </string>
    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page3">-->
    <string name="room4Page3Text">
        Vuk Stefanović Karadžić was appreciated in Europe: he was a member of Vienna’s, Berlin’s
        and Saint Petersburg’s Academy of Science, he was a member of Science Societies in Krakow,
        Moscow, Göttingen and Paris, and he was also distinguished by Russian and Austrian –
        Hungarian emperor, by Prussian kin and by Russian Academy of Science. He died in Vienna
        as 77 years old, 1864. Vuk’s mortal remains werw carried over in Belgrade in 1897. and
        buried in port of St. Michael\'s Cathedral, next to the Dositej Obradović’s grave. Personal
        belongings Vuk was carrying in his bag while he was travelling. There are: shaving
        accessories, brush for cleaning shoes and clothes and nail accessories. Non - essential
        items during his journey were: stationery, a travel clock, chaplet, cigar – holder, a
        sack for tobacco and holster.  Vuk Karadžić is remebered by fes on his head. Fes is a hat
        made from čoha, red material, in the shape of cone with offset top, with even number of
        black aiglet. The name of this kind of hat is from city Fez in Morocco. During the slavery
        of Turkey fes were wearing Serbs and other non – Muslims. Vuk was wearing a fes in enslave
        and exempt Serbia, but in Vienna hw was wearing fes as the part of clothes which was mixture
        of European and Oriental style. Vuk was impressive figure, already well – known, dressed in:
        shirt, vest, blazer, and pants by European style. Of course, he was wearing red fes,
        long moustache, but he couldn’t walk without his crutch.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="vukova_diploma">Vuk\'s Degree from Moscow University</string>
    <string name="vukova_diploma_detail">Vuk\'s Degree from Moscow University, Moscow 14. III 1828.</string>
    <string name="putna_torba">Vuk\'s traveling bag</string>
    <string name="putna_torba_detail">Vuk\'s traveling bag, leather and wood, Vienna, 19th Century</string>
    <string name="crvena_coka">Vuk\'s fez</string>
    <string name="crvena_coka_detail">Vuk\'s fez, part of Turkish national costume</string>
    <string name="mladi_vuk">Young Vuk Karadžić</string>
    <string name="mladi_vuk_detail">Pavel Đurković, Young Vuk Karadžić, 19th Century</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    //Vukovo delo
    <!--<editor-fold desc="Room5">-->
    <string name="room5Title">Vuk\'s work</string>

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page1">-->
    <string name="room5Page1Text">
        After the failure of the First Serbian Uprising, young Vuk went to Vienna. He wrote a writ
        about the failure of the Uprising, which Jernej Kopitar, the censor for the Slavic languages,
        found interesting. He wanted to meet this young man who was expressing himself in folk language.
        So Vuk, with his guidance and tips, started collecting folk songs and preparing the grammar
        of folk speech. In 1814 in Vienna, he published a collection of folk songs which he named
        Mala prostonarodna slaveno-serbska pesnarica. The same year, he published
        Pismenica serbskoga jezika po govoru prostoga naroda napisana, the first Serbian grammar
        based on the folk speech. No matter the incompletion, this work is valuable as the first
        grammar of the folk speech. In 1818 Vuk Karadžić published the first dictionary of the
        Serbian language, which contained 26,270 words that were publicly used. The same year he
        prepared a second edition of hid grammar which was translated into German a few years later
        by Jacob Grimm. In the second edition of the dictionary, there were 47,427 words collected
        from folk speech. Vuk has been working on the preparation of the third edition
        of the vocabulary for years, and has personally, by himself, made amendments.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="pismenica">Писменицa сербскога језика</string>
    <string name="pismenica_detail">Вук С. Караџић, Писменицa сербскога језика по говору простога народа написану, Беч, 1815.</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page2">-->
    <string name="room5Page2Text">
        Vuk traveled, along the Balkan Peninsula, Germany, Austria, Russia and some parts of Europe,
        most often moved by his call. During his travels in Serbia, Montenegro, Croatia, and Hungary
        he recorded folk songs. Following the Romanticism spirit, which in the recording of poems
        recognized the true expression of folk creativity, Vuk recorded proverbs in order to meet
        and study peoples and their traditions. In European circles, numerous scientists and poets
        have been interested in Vuk\'s writings, such as: Gete, Walter Scott, Pushkin, Tomazeo, but
        also many others who translated, interpreted and imitated them. The most important one was
        certainly Jacob Grimm, thanks to whose translations into German, folk creation became
        accessible and recognizable by its originality, unusual heroism and an abundance of
        characters and events. With the support of Jernej Kopitar, Vuk began to record folk songs.
        In the first collection of songs from 1814, about 100 lyric and 6 epic songs were published.
        The following year, he released another collection of folk songs called
        Narodna serbska pesnarica and found songs that were performed by guslars Tesan Podrugovic and Filip Visnjic.
    </string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page3">-->
    <string name="room5Page3Text">
        After a great success with the songs, Vuk began to work on the collection of all kinds of
        folk proverbs. The first collection of stories by the Narodne srpske pripovijetke was
        printed in 1821 in Vienna. Parallel to the collecting of poems and tales, Vuk also recorded
        folk proverbs. In 1836 in Cetinje, Montenegro, he published the Narodne srpske poslovice
        which he dedicated to the Prince-Bishop Petar Petrovic Njegos. He devoted himself to
        describing folklore whose terms he interpreted and described in the Serbian dictionary.
        Apart from the work on the reform of the Serbian language, Vuk Karadzic also did historiographical work.
        As a participant of the First Serbian Uprising, he prepared material on events until 1814.
        This material was handed over to the famous German historian, Leopold Ranke, who later wrote his work The Serbian Revolution.
        In 1828, he published the book Milos Obrenovic knjaz Serbiji, in which he wrote about the reign of Prince Milos Obrenovic.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="srpski_rjecnik">Serbian Dictionary</string>
    <string name="srpski_rjecnik_detail">Serbian Dictionary, first edition, Vienna 1818.</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page4">-->
    <string name="room5Page4Text">
        The rule that we are using today, which has enabled Serbian language to become one of the
        simplest languages ​​for reading and writing, is Write as you say, read how it is written.
        It wasn’t so easy to achieve this simple and logical phrase. Dositej Obradovic established
        the basic features and directions of the new Serbian culture and literacy, advocating for a
        democratic spirit, critical principles and the use of the folk language in literature, but
        unfortunately, he was unable to live long enough to see his ideas turn into action. However,
        Dositej certainly, in addition to many other exceptional individuals, directly influenced
        Vuk, who rounded up the process of reforming the folk language and literature.
        Prior to the Vuk\'s reforms in use, there were simultaneously used: the simple-folk Serbian
        language, the Church Slavonic and the Slavo-Serbian language.With the expansion of the
        national spirit, it was obvious that the introduction of the folk language into Serbian
        culture was the only opportunity for its advancement. Applying the rule: For each voice,
        one letter, Vuk took 24 letters from the Old Slavic alphabet, dismissed the dysfunctional
        ones and added six new letters: j, lj, nj, đ, dž and ć and thus achieved that the Serbian
        language has one of the most perfect spellings in the world. With the reform of the Serbian
        language and introducing the letter j, Vuk gained many enemies, many of whom were among the
        church people. The reason for this was the deviation from the church language and the
        introduction of letters from the Latin languages, which was interpreted as the Catholicising of the Orthodox people.
    </string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page5">-->
    <string name="room5Page5Text">
        However, thanks to the character and persistence that Vuk has had, today we can proudly say
        that the Serbian alphabet is one of the rare phonetic alphabets. To what extent Vuk\'s reform
        was remarkable proves the Irish drama writer George Benard Shaw, who left a huge sum of
        money as a prize for the one who is able to reform the English alphabet according to the
        model of the Vuk\'s Cyrillic. The reform of the Serbian language and alphabet, which was
        begun by Dositej Obradovic, took the unofficial victory in 1847. At that time, the book
        Rat za srpski jezik i pravopis by Djura Danicic and the first collection of poems by
        Branko Radicevic were published, which, along with the translation of the New Testament,
        were written in the folk language or by the Vuk\'s spelling. In the same year, Njegos\'s
        Gorski Vijenac was also published, also written in the folk language, but the old spelling,
        since this famous poet was a church figure.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="djura_danicic">Đura Daničić</string>
    <string name="djura_danicic_detail">Steva Todorović, Đura Daničić, oil on canvas, 19th century.</string>
    <string name="gorski_venac">Goski Vijenac</string>
    <string name="gorski_venac_detail">Petar II Petrović Njegoš, Goski Vijenac Vienna 1847.</string>
    <string name="branko_radicevic">Branko Radičević</string>
    <string name="branko_radicevic_detail">Unknown author, Branko Radičević, oil on canvas, 19th Century </string>
    <string name="novi_zavet">Bible</string>
    <string name="novi_zavet_detail">Bible, translation by Vuk Karadžić, Vienna 1818.</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page6">-->
    <string name="room5Page6Text">
        An important historical meeting took place in Vienna, March 28, 1850. Slovene, Serbian and
        Croatian philologists, including Vuk, met in order to agree and unify, as far as possible,
        on the matter of literature. On that occasion, a Literary Agreement was signed in which they
        proposed a unique Serbo-Croatian language and spelling. The victory of the Vuk\'s reform of
        language and spelling was only established in 1868 when the spelling in Serbia was officially
        accepted and introduced into the school system. Vuk Stefanovic Karadzic died in Vienna in 1864.
        The remains were transferred to Belgrade in 1897 and with great honor they were buried in
        the port of the Assembly Church, next to Dositej Obradovic.

    </string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    //Dositejevo delo
    <!--<editor-fold desc="Room6">-->
    <string name="room6Title">Dositej\'s work</string>

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page1">-->
    <string name="room6Page1Text">
        After the publication of the Pismo Haralampiju and the autobiographical work
        Zivot i prikljucenija  in 1784 in Leipzig, Slovo poucitelno was printed in which
        Dositej rises against the use of incomprehensible words and expressions which were used in
        literature and in words. In the previously announced work, the Sovjeti zdravog razuma
        from the same year, Dositej criticizes prejudice, superstition and goodwill, and favors
        the idea of ​​free thinking and moral quality. During his stay in the Hopovo Monastery and
        later on his travels, Dositej Obradović read and translated the fables of Ezop, Fedra,
        Lafonten, Abstemius and Lesing. He prepared and published 160 fables translated into
        Serbian in 1788 in Leipzig. Next, in 1789, after the Austrian and Russian military, with
        the help of the Serb volunteers, liberated Belgrade from the Turks, on October 9, the song
        Pjesna was published on the Serb insurrection dedicated to Karadjordje and the insurrections.
        Because of the refrain, it became known to the people by the name of Vostani Serbije.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="sovjeti">Sovjeti zdravog razuma</string>
    <string name="sovjeti_detail">Sovjeti zdravog razuma, Leipzig, 1784.</string>
    <string name="basne">Fables</string>
    <string name="basne_detail">Dositej Obradović, Fables, Leipzig, 1784.</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page2">-->
    <string name="room6Page2Text">
        Sobranije raznih naravoucitelnih vescej was published in Vienna in 1793, in which the
        problems of philosophy, history, ethics and aesthetics were discussed in parallel with
        examples from the literature of the European peoples. The second part of this work,
        called Mezimac, was posthumously published in 1818. The work Etika from 1803, which contains
        anecdotes, folk stories and proverbs, should be added to this work in order to bring the
        Serbian reader closer to the code of ethical principles. Although traveling the world,
        Dositej Obradovic wholeheartedly helped the Serbs in the struggle for liberation from the
        Turkish authorities, first sending donations and various confidential missions until he
        eventually finally came to Serbia. Then, already in late years, he comes to help, not only
        by quill and acquired knowledge, but according to the legend also by potatoes, who first came to Serbia with him.
        In the liberated Serbia he spent the last five years of his life. He introduced new reforms
        in teaching and established a new understanding of the role of women in society, demanding
        that female children get the opportunity to attend school. Only a few months after being
        appointed as the first Minister of Education, Dositej Obradovic died on March 28, 1811 in
        Belgrade where he was buried in the port of the Assembly Church.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="sobranie">Sobranije raznih naravoučitelnih veštej</string>
    <string name="sobranie_detail">Dositej Obradović, Sobranije raznih naravoučitelnih veštej, Vienna 1793.</string>
    <string name="etika">Ethics</string>
    <string name="etika_detail">Dositej Obradović, Ethics, Venice, 1803.</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    //Vukova porodica
    <!--<editor-fold desc="Room7">-->
    <string name="room7Title">Vuk\'s family</string>

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page1">-->
    <string name="room7Page1Text">
        Arriving to Vienna, Vuk married his landlord’s daughter, austrian Ana Marija Kraus.
        Just the two of their thirteen children, Mina and Dimitrije, had outlived their parents and
        therefore Vuk himself wrote that it had seemed to him that only his literary works would
        remain after his children. Mother Ana practically had raised the children on her own, because
        Vuk travelled for months, visiting various regions and writing down words, sayings and folk songs.
        With the object and effort to give their children good education, they had been lacking in money.
        In many ways and with difficulties they managed to provide the children with elementary
        conditions for living and studying. Ana tried to keep the children healthy and nurtured,
        and Vuk himself made the toys for them. Life in the Karadžić family changed for the better
        as Vuk received the russian pension, and also the pension of prince Miloš.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="vuk_ana_detail">Vuk and Ana Karadžić</string>
    <string name="vuk_ana">Vuk and Ana Karadžić</string>
    <string name="igracke">Toys</string>
    <string name="igracke_detail">Toys made of boxwood by Vuk Karadžić himself, Vienna 19th Century</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page2">-->
    <string name="room7Page2Text">
        Vuk’s and Ana\'s seventh child, Vilhelmina Mina Karadžić, was born in 1828 in Vienna.
        Mina, although without full-time education, attended both piano and painting lessons.
        She was fond of learning languages, and besides German and her father’s Serbian,
        she mastered French, Italian, and then English. Alongside with her parents, she visited
        museums and galleries, where she absorbed the beauty of artwork. Mina found interest in
        painting, which she learned from famous artists. Among fifty of her drawings and portraits,
        her self-portrait is preserved, as is the portrait of brother Dimitrije. Hoping for a
        Russian scholarship for painting in Italy and France, which she unfortunately didn’t get,
        fifteen-year-old Mina starts aiming for literature education. She wrote poems and
        translated folk tales, helping her father to perform his correspondence. Mina Karadzić
        severely incurred her father\'s death in 1864, as well as her mother’s in 1876.
        She was completely devastated when she received a letter in 1877 that her 19-year-old son
        Janko died, who attended military school in Russia. After that, she dedicated her work to
        publishing her father\'s works in Belgrade, Vienna and Petrograd. Mina gave her father\'s
        inheritance to the Kingdom of Serbia before death, thanks to which the personal belongings,
        letters, books and paintings of Vuk, Mina and Karadzić\'s family have been preserved in the
        Museum of Vuk and Dositej of the National Museum in Belgrade. Among them is a portrait of Branko Radičević.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="mina_sin">Mina Karadžić with her son Janko Vukomanović</string>
    <string name="mina_sin_detail">Mina Karadžić with her son Janko Vukomanović</string>
    <string name="dimitrije_karadzic">Dimitrije Karadžić</string>
    <string name="dimitrije_karadzic_detail">Sveta Mandić, Dimitrije Karadžić, 1858.</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page3">-->
    <string name="room7Page3Text">
        The closeness of Mina Karadzic and Branko Radičević,  Serbianbranko romantic poet, is still a
        topic of interest to a large number of researchers. Mina returned and embellished her
        affection and sympathy painting some of Branko\'s portraits. In her late years, she wrote
        Memories of Branko, revealing the extreme closeness and great friendship shared by both of them.
        What really Mina’s and Branko\'s relationship looked like, what really existed between a
        young poet, suffering from a severe, incurable disease and a beautiful girl who was the
        inspiration and unachievable love of many scholars of that period, remains to be speculated.
        However, it is interesting that Branko, at the moment of his disease beginning to take a toll,
        sent all of his things to his friend, keeping only one of Mina’s portraits.
        We must not forget that Branko was a poet of a romantic epoch and that his love therefore
        had to be ideal and idealized. Five years after Branko\'s death, Mina Karadžiž married Aleksa Vukomanović,
        founder of the Department of Serbian Language, History and Literature and Fr. Ljubica\'s nephew.
    </string>

    <!-- Image titles-->
    <string name="mina_karadzic">Mina Karadžić</string>
    <string name="mina_karadzic_detail">Mina Karadžić as a 16 year old girl</string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page4">-->
    <string name="room7Page4Text">
        Vuk\'s son Dimitrije was a great hope, not only for Karadžić\'s family, but also hope of the
        entire Serbia. After studying in Trieste and Klosterbruck, the Government of Serbia
        scholarshipped his education in Berlin and later in Antwerp. However, Dimitri liked the
        freedom of life and alcohol, so he spent a lot of money, which caused him to get into debts
        in his student days. Initially, this way of life and rising debts did not affect his career.
        He became a second-class captain and a fortification professor at the Artillery School in Belgrade.
        However, after Vuk\'s death, he began to pay off debts with his father\'s property and his spendthrift way of life came out.
        Because of the intemperance in drinking and gambling, he was a bad example for young soldiers,
        and therefore for Serbia. He was forced to leave his teaching position at the Artillery school
        and went to Russia where he served as an officer. All of the requests his sister Mina sent
        him to calm down and change the way of living, did not help Dimitrije. As a Russian volunteer,
        he fought in the Serbian-Turkish war together with Mina’s younger son Janko,
        who returned from the war with a medal for courage. From the side-effects of battle and disease,
        Janko died in Russia in 1878, while his uncle Dimitrije died several years later.
    </string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    <!--</editor-fold>-->

    //Divanhana
    <!--<editor-fold desc="Room8">-->
    <string name="room8Title">Divanhana</string>

    <!--<editor-fold desc="Page1">-->
    <string name="room8Page1Text">
        Tradiotional way of buliding homes in Ottoman Empire implicited separation publicly from
        privately and male from female. Divanhana is a room for public way of living, where the guests,
        business partners and others were coming and were not sibilngs of the owner of house.
        Divanhana is risen from floor ypented by wooden pillars. This room was separated from
        other rooms used for other daily activities. Divanhana in Museum of Vuk and Dositej is
        great example of that kind of construction. Edge of divanhana is named as ,,divan” and
        that is the word stemming. That is a bench where the gusest used to sit, and the host was
        sitting in the central place, a bit risen, and on that way his social status is accented.
        In the case of visti of some magnate, the host gave place to honored guest. Reputable and
        opulent Serbs took concept of building from Turkey until the liberation and modernization of Serbia.
        Interior of divanhana were simple, on the floors and on the walls were hanging colorful rugs,
        and ornamental dishes were positioned on the shelves. In craftsman’s divanhana was some
        object made by himself or by his ancestor. Later, in Christian houses were used photographies
        and sculptures for decoration. One segment of TV serial ,,Vuk Karadžić“ where Dositej Obradović
        is talking to Karađorđe, dukes and students during the opening of Great school was filmed in 
        divanhana of Museum of Vuk and Dositej. Monodrama ,,My father Vuk Karadžić“ was filmed in divanhana.
    </string>

    <!--</editor-fold>-->
    <!--</editor-fold>-->

</resources>